Register of the Dieter Spethmann Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dieter Spethmann papers,
1966-2002
2002C61
Spethmann, Dieter, 1926-
161 manuscript boxes (67.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Relates to German, European and international economic conditions, and especially to the steel industry.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1926, March 27 Born, Essen, Germany
1945-1948 Studied law and economics
1952-1954 Involved in activities to settle German pre-war debts
1952-1955 Legal Department, Gelsenkirchener Bergwerks-AG
1953 Doctor of Law (Dr. Jur.)
1955-1958 Personal assistant to the chairman, August Thyssen-Hütte AG
1958-1962 Financial manager, August Thyssen-Hütte AG
1962-1964 Member, Executive Board, Thyssen Handelsunion AG
1964-1970 Chairman, Executive Board, Thyssen Edelstahlwerke AG
1970-1973 Member, Executive Board, Thyssen AG
1973 Apr.-1991 Chairman, Board of Managing Directors, Thyssen AG
Scope and Content Note
These papers focus on the latter part of Dieter Spethmann's career in the German steel industry and as chairman of the global Thyssen concern. They provide information about the activities of Thyssen, one of seventeen companies formed from the United Steel Works, a combine of steel companies founded in 1926 and dismantled after World War II. The papers also document the participation of Spethmann in the growth of a united Europe, particularly through the European Community and the reunification of Germany, and globalization.
In addition to material concerning Thyssen and the steel industry, there are also some files relating to special projects nurtured by Spethmann, such as his magnetic train (Transrapid), which is contained in the SUBJECT FILE.
Texts of speeches represent the bulk of SPEECHES AND WRITINGS. In most cases a final typescript is the sole format for each speech or article. However, the unnumbered items at the end of the series typically contain collateral materials such as correspondence relating to the invitation to speak, clippings, reports, earlier speeches by Spethmann or others, and statistical tables.
Spethmann was heavily involved in the Industrial Circle for Foreign Affairs (Industriekreis für Auslandsbeziehungen), which was established circa 1955. The Industrial Circle was an informal group of about thirty important industrial and business leaders centered on the Düsseldorf-Essen-Cologne area that met ten to fifteen times a year. At each meeting a prominent guest visited for dinner, usually at Castle Jägerhof in Düsseldorf. After dinner the guest spoke briefly on a subject related to the guest's official position, followed by an open discussion. The meetings were closed; no press was present, and participants were obliged not to quote publicly from the meetings. The Circle's managers included Sigismund von Braun, circa 1976-1993, and Klaus Blech, 1994-2001. Rough summaries of the discussions with guests during the von Braun period are included in the INDUSTRIAL CIRCLE CORRESPONDENCE/Guests of honor subseries.
The HANS SPETHMANN FILE contains writings by Dieter's father, who was a geographer and historian of economics. In 1923 he left his university teaching post to accept an invitation by the coal mining industry of the Ruhr, where he did research. Included in this collection are two of his writings about the Ruhr, Das Ruhrgebiet (3 volumes) and the unpublished "Der Ruhrbergbau und der Zweite Weltkrieg," which chronicles the history of the Ruhr coal mining industry during World War II. He died in 1957.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
International economic relations.; Steel industry and trade--Germany (West); Germany (West)--Economic conditions.; Europe--Economic conditions--1945-; Germany.; Europe.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1984-1991. (Box 1-7)
  Book, correspondence, and interview transcript, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1978(?)-1993. (Box 8-36)
  Clippings, correspondence, invitations, lists, maps, printed matter, programs, seating plans, and telephone messages, arranged in two subseries: (1) the bulk in segments by one or more years, thereunder by name of correspondent, and (2) a small volume by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1965-2002. (Box 37-66)
  Arranged in two subseries: (1) items numbered from 1 to 80, and (2) unnumbered items, which are arranged chronologically. In most cases a final typescript is the sole format for each speech or article. However, the unnumbered items typically include collateral materials such as articles, charts, clippings, correspondence, invitations, lists, notes, printed matter, programs, and statistical tables
- Conference, Meeting, and Interview Materials, 1977-1992. (Box 67-88)
  Articles, briefing papers, charts, clippings, correspondence, invitations, itineraries, lists, notes, printed matter, programs, reports, statistical tables, and texts of speeches, from conferences and meetings Spethmann attended, arranged alphabetically by name of event, organization, public official, or other entity
- Subject File, 1952-2001(bulk 1987-1995). (Box 89-97)
  Articles, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and reports, arranged alphabetically by subject. Some interfiled Thyssen material is included
- Thyssen Public Affairs File, 1970-1991. (Box 98-103)
  Lectures, minutes, publication, and typescripts, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- File on Thyssen Involvement in East Germany, 1991. (Box 104-106)
  Clippings, correspondence, printed matter, and reports, unarranged. Includes background materials for Spethmann's meeting with Helmut Kohl, 1991 Mar. 20
- Thyssen General Business Meeting (Hauptversammlung) File, 1970-1991. (Box 107-110)
  Minutes and leader's guide, arranged alphabetically by physical form, thereunder chronologically
- Thyssen Subject File, 1966-1996(bulk 1985-1991). (Box 111-126)
  Articles, charts, clippings, correspondence, grant applications, minutes, printed matter, and statistical tables, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Supervisory Board Functions in Other Companies File, 1979-1995. (Box 127-131)
  Articles, clippings, correspondence, notes, press releases, printed matter, reports, statistical tables, arranged alphabetically by name of company
- Industrial Circle Guestbooks and List (Industriekreis Gästebücher und Aufstellung), 1955-2001. (Box 132-133)
  List of guests and guestbooks, the latter arranged chronologically
- Industrial Circle Gatherings (Zusammenkünfte) File, 1966-2001. (Box 134-141)
  Invitations, letters sent, lists, and seating charts, arranged chronologically by meeting date
- Industrial Circle Correspondence (Korrespondenz), 1971-2001(bulk 1980s-1990s). (Box 141-157)
  Correspondence, curricula vitae, and summaries, arranged alphabetically by category of correspondent, thereunder by name
- Hans Spethmann File, 1933-1954. (Box 158-159)
  Book and manuscript, arranged chronologically
- Audiocassette, 2002. (Box 159)
  Spethmann interview, Hoover Institution Archives, 2002 Mar. 14
- Videocassette, 2002. (Box 159)
  Spethmann interview, "Continuity and Change in the German Steel Industry," with Gerald D. Feldman, 2002 Mar. 15
- Compact Disc, 2002. (Box 159)
  Spethmann's numbered speeches and writings, 1-28, 28a, 29-80
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1984-1991
  - Book, 1991. (Box 6)
    Magnetfelder: Dieter Spethmann zum 65. Geburtstag, herausgegeben von Elisabeth Birte Spethmann (Magnetic fields: Dieter Spethmann upon his 65th birthday, published by Elisabeth Birte Spethmann)
  - Correspondence
    - 40th professional anniversary (40 Jahre Berufsjubiläum), 1989 (Box 7)
    - 60th birthday, 1986 (Box 1-4)
    - 65th birthday, 1991
      - A-K (Box 5)
      - L-Z (Box 6)
    - French Legion of Honor (Franz. Ehrenlegion), 1984 (Box 7)
    - German Order of Merit (Bundesverdienstkreuz), 1986
    - Honorary doctorate in engineering (Dr. Ing. Eh. Professor), 1990
    - Honorary member of Ironworks Workers (Ehrenmitglied Eisenhüttenleute), 1985
  - Interview transcript, 2002 Mar. 15., See also VIDEOCASSETTE (Box 6)
    Conversations #234: Dr. Dieter Spethmann, "Continuity and Change in the German Steel Industry," with Gerald D. Feldman, Institute of International Studies, University of California, Berkeley. In English.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1978(?)-1993
  - General
    - 1978(?) to 1987 Dec. 31
      - A-B (Box 8)
      - B-E (Box 9)
      - F (Box 10)
      - G (Box 9)
      - H (Box 10)
      - I-K (Box 11)
      - L-O (Box 12)
      - P-S (excluding Sch, St) (Box 13)
      - Sch, St (Box 14)
      - T (Box 14-15)
      - U-Z (Box 15)
    - 1988-1990
      - A-B (Box 16)
      - C-G (Box 17)
      - H-K (Box 18)
      - K-Q (Box 19)
      - R-S (Box 20)
      - T-Z (Box 21)
    - 1988
      - A-R (Box 22)
      - S-Z (Box 23)
    - 1989
      - A-K (Box 23)
      - L-Z (Box 24)
    - 1990
      - A-B (Box 24)
      - C-O (Box 25)
      - P-Z (Box 26)
    - 1991
      - A-G (Box 27)
      - H-M (Box 28)
      - N-Z (Box 29)
    - 1992-1993
      - A-G (Box 30)
      - H-L (Box 31)
      - M-R (Box 32)
      - S-Z (Box 33)
  - Miscellany. Hunting invitations (Jagdeinladungen), 1982-1990 (Box 8, 36)
  - Birrenbach, Kurt, 1968-1985 (Box 34-35)
  - Bundesverband der Deutschen Industrie (BDI) (Dr. Siegfried Mann), 1983-1986 (Box 34)
  - Oppenheimer, Fritz E. and Mrs. Elsbeth, 1960-1984 (Box 21)
  - West German government (Bundesregierung), 1974-1991. (Box 36)
    Includes Martin Bangemann, Helmut Kohl, Wolfgang Schäuble, Rudolf Seiters, Gerhard Stoltenberg, and others
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1965-2002
  - General
    - General
      - 1966-1970 (Box 42)
      - 1971 (Box 43)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 45)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 46)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 47)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 48)
      - 1978 (Box 43)
      - 1979 (Box 49)
      - 1980 (Box 53)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 54)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 55)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 58)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 59)
      - 1988 (Box 41)
      - 1989 (Box 62)
      - 1990 (Box 63)
    - Deutsche Edelstahlwerke AG, 1965-1970 (2 vols.) (Box 37)
    - Economic policy (Wirtschaftspolitik), 1966-1970 (2 vols.) (Box 40)
    - Management (Unternehmensführung), 1966-1970 (2 vols.) (Box 40-41)
  - Numbered items., See also COMPACT DISC
    - 1. "Organisationsprobleme im Grossunternehmen" (Problems of organization in large scale enterprises), speech, Frankfurter Gespräch der List Gesellschaft, Frankfurt, 1966 Mar. 3-5 (Box 50)
    - 2. "Zur konjunkturellen Entwicklung in der BRD" (To cyclical business development in West Germany), speech, Tagung TIME-LIFE International, Juan-les-Pins, France, 1966 June 17-18 (Box 50)
    - 3. "Die wichtigsten zukünftigen Aufgaben und Schwierigkeiten der Management-Forschung aus der Sicht der Unternehmensführung" (The prime future needs and difficulties for research in management from management's perspective), speech, B.I.A.C. Seminar on the Promotion of Research for Industrial Management, Hertfordshire, England, 1967 Oct. 4-7 (Box 50)
    - 4. "Unternehmensführung heute und morgen" (Top management today and tomorrow), speech, Deutsche Volkswirtschaftliche Gesellschaft, Essen, 1966 Nov. 14 (Box 50)
    - 5. "Top Management Today and Tomorrow," English translation, speech, Wirtschaftspublizistischen Vereinigung, Düsseldorf, 1967 Jan. 31 (Box 50)
    - 6. "Geld- und Kapitalmarktprobleme aus der Sicht der Industrie" (Money market problems and capital market problems from the perspective of industry), speech, Baden-Badener Unternehmergespräche/Regionalgespräch, Krefeld, 1967 Mar. 9 (Box 50)
    - 7. "Anforderungen des modernen Betriebes an die überfachliche Qualifikation des jungen Akademikers (aus der Sicht der Wirtschaft)" (Modern business operation requirements against the overly technical qualifications of young university graduates {from the perspective of the economy}), speech, Jugend- und Bildungsausschuss der Bundesvereinigung Deutscher Arbeitgeberverbände, Berlin, 1968 May 16 (Box 50)
    - 8. "Gedanken zum 20-jährigen Jubiläum der D-Mark" (Thoughts on the 20th anniversary of the German Mark), speech, Rotary Club, Krefeld, 1968 July 22) (Box 50)
    - 9. "Gefährliche Sucht nach Grösse?" (Dangerous search for bigness?), essay, Handelsblatt, 1968 Aug. 16-17 (Box 50)
    - 10. "Flexibilitätsüberlegungen bei Investitionsprogrammen" (Flexible deliberations with capital expenditure programs), speech, 22. Deutscher Betriebswirtschafter-Tag, Berlin, 1968 Sep. 30 (Box 50)
    - 11. "Die technologische Lücke zwischen den USA and Westeuropa aus deutscher Sicht" (The technological gap between the USA and western Europe from the German perspective), speech, Wilton Park Conference, Wilton Park, England, 1968 Dec. 12 (Box 50)
    - 12. "Integrationsförderung durch zwischenstaatliche Kooperation und Konzentration" (Promotion of integration through international cooperation and concentration), speech, FIW-Symposium II, Innsbruck, 1969 Feb. 21 (Box 50)
    - 13. "Unternehmensführung und Diversifikation" (Business management and diversification), speech, Centre d'Etudes Industrielles, Geneva, 1969 May 13 (Box 50)
    - 14. "Internationale Liquidität aus deutscher Sicht" (International liquidity from the German perspective), speech, Wilton Park Conference, Wilton Park, England, 1969 May 23-25 (Box 50)
    - 15. "Probleme des Aussenhandels und der Währungspolitik" (Problems of foreign trade and monetary policy), speech, Gruppe Niederrhein des Wirtschaftsrats der CDU, Krefeld, 1969 July 16 (Box 50)
    - 16. "Gedanken zur Unternehmenskonzentration" (Thoughts on corporate concentration), speech, Rechts- und Staatswissenschaftliche Vereinigung, 1969 Nov. 3 (Box 50)
    - 17. "Entwicklungstendenzen des Weltstahlmarktes" (Development trends of the world steel market), speech, C. R. Poensgen-Stiftung, Düsseldorf, 1970 Mar. 10 (Box 50)
    - 18. "Internationale Unternehmenszusammenschlüsse und Kooperationsvereinbarungen" (International corporate mergers and cooperation agreements), speech, Hermann Ehlers Stiftung, Kiel, 1970 June 19 (Box 50)
    - 19. "Möglichkeiten und Grenzen der Einkommens- und Vermögenspolitik" (Capabilities and limits of the income policy and wealth policy), speech, Arbeitsgemeinschaft christlich-demokratischer DGB-Gewerkschafter, Duisburg, 1970 Sep. 25 (Box 50)
    - 20. "Der Unternehmer und die Politik" (The entrepreneur and politics), speech, Gemeinschaft junger Unternehmer bei der Industrie- und Handelskammer zu Krefeld, 1970 Sep. 28 (Box 50)
    - 21. "Führungsprobleme in den 70er Jahren" (Leadership problems in the seventies), speech, Zwei-Löwen-Club, Münster, 1970 Oct. 8 (Box 50)
    - 22. "Möglichkeiten und Grenzen der pretialen Lenkung in grossen Unternehmungen" (Capabilities and limits of control in large enterprises), speech, Dinkelbach-Kreis, Duisburg, 1970 Dec. 4 (Box 50)
    - 23. "Umweltschutz in der industriellen Gesellschaft" (Environmental protection in the industrial society), speech, Deutsch-Französischer Kreis, Düsseldorf, 1973 Dec. 11 (Box 50)
    - 24. "Wirtschafts- und Unternehmenspolitik im Spannungsfeld" (Economic policy and corporate policy in tug-of-war), speech, C. R. Poensgen-Stiftung, Krefeld, 1974 Nov. 28 (Box 50)
    - 25. "Energy and Steel," interim report (Zwischenbericht), Ad Hoc Working Group on Energy, International Iron and Steel Institute (IISI) annual meetings and conference, 1976 Oct. 11. (Box 50)
      In English
    - 26. "Zur zukünftigen Zusammenarbeit zwischen Rohstoff- und Industrieländern" (To the future cooperation between developing and developed countries), speech, C. R. Poensgen-Stiftung, Krefeld (?), 1977 Apr. 21 (Box 50)
    - 27. "Stahl an einer kritischen Schwelle" (Steel at a critical threshold), article, List Forum, 1977 June (Box 50)
    - 28. "Rationalisierung und Schaffung neuer Arbeitsplätze – ein Gegensatz?" (Streamlining and establishing new workplaces - a contradiction?), speech, 31. Deutscher Betriebswirtschafter-Tag, Berlin, 1977 Sep. 18 (Box 50)
    - 29. "Die Situation der europäischen Stahlindustrie" (The situation of the European steel industry), speech, Zürcher Volkswirtschaftliche Gesellschaft, Zurich, 1977 Dec. 14 (Box 50)
    - 30. "Wirtschaftspolitik im internationalen Spannungsfeld" (Economic policy in the international tug-of-war), speech, Übersee-Club, Hamburg, 1978 May 8 (Box 50)
    - 31. "Erwartungshorizonte in Hochschule und Praxis" (Horizons of expectation in university and practical experience), speech, Mitgliderversammlung des Vereins zur Förderung des Instituts für Bankwirtschaft und Bankrecht an der Universität zu Köln e.V., Cologne, 1979 June 18 (Box 50)
    - 32. "Chairman's Address," International Iron and Steel Institute (IISI) annual meetings and conference, Sydney, 1979 Oct. 14-17. (Box 50)
    - 33. "Cogestion" (Co-Determination), speech, Belgische Handelskammer, Brussels, 1979 Nov. 8. (Box 50)
      In French
    - 34. "Chairman's Address," International Iron and Steel Institute (IISI) annual meetings and conference, Madrid, 1980 Oct. 5-8. (Box 50)
    - 35. "Das internationale Eisen- und Stahlinstitut – eine Zwischenbilanz" (The International Iron and Steel Institute – an interim statement), Ifo-Studien, Number 2-3, 1981 (Box 50)
    - 36. "Eröffnungsreferat" (Opening address), Mitgliederversammlung der Wirtschaftsvereinigung Eisen- und Stahlindustrie, Düsseldorf, 1982 May 11 (Box 50)
    - 37. "Ist Stagnation unser Schicksal?" (Is stagnation our fate?), speech, Hamburger Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung – Hamburgische Welt-Wirtschafts-Archiv (HWWA), Hamburg, 1982 June 16 (Box 50)
    - 38. "Internationale Wirtschaftspolitik und industrielle Strukturen" (International economic policy and industrial structures), speech, Mitgliederversammlung der deutschen Gruppe des Forex-Club, Düsseldorf, 1983 Mar. 11 (Box 50)
    - 39. "EUROFER – Selbsthilfe der europäischen Stahlindustrie in der Krise" (European confederation of iron and steel industries – self help of the European steel industry in crisis), in Standpunkte und Perspektiven, Festschrift für Herbert W. Köhler, Düsseldorf und Vienna, 1984 (Box 51)
    - 40. "Industriestandort Bundesrepublik – Rückzug ohne Ende?" (West German industrial base – retreat without end?), speech, Industrie- und Handelsclub Ost-Westfalen e.V., Bielefeld, 1985 Jan. 16 (Box 51)
    - 41. "The Steel Crisis in Europe: Where Do We Come From? Where Do We Go?" speech, The Empire Club of Canada, Toronto, 1985 Jan. 31. (Box 51)
    - 42. "Aufgaben der Unternehmensleitung" (Tasks of administrative management), speech, 77. Baden-Badener Unternehmergespräche, Baden-Baden, 1986 Apr. 22 (Box 51)
    - 43. "Industrielle Perspektiven in der Bundesrepublik Deutschland" (Industrial prospects in West Germany), speech, Deutscher Wirtschaftsclub in Mailand, Milan, 1987 May 12 (Box 51)
    - 44. "Die Wirtschaftspolitik der Bundesländer: Auf dem Weg zum Neomerkantilismus?" (The economic policy of the German states: on the road to neo-mercantilism?), speech, Expertengespräch der List Gesellschaft, Frankfurt, 1987 Apr. 3 (Box 51)
    - 45. "Stahl im Blickpunkt – Die Internationalen Aspekte einer Krise" (Steel in focus – the internationl aspects of a crisis), speech, Rotary Club, Düsseldorf, 1987 May 25 (Box 51)
    - 46. "The Survival of National Basic Industry: Steel as an Example of Worldwide Challenge," speech, Ford European Advisory Council, Geneva, 1987 Oct. 15-16. (Box 51)
    - 47. "Aufgaben der Unternehmensleitung" (Tasks of administrative management), speech, 81. Baden-Badener Unternehmergespräche, Baden-Baden, 1988 Apr. 25 (Box 51)
    - 48. "Auflösung des Normalarbeitsverhältnisses?" (Disintegration of normal employment?), introductory remarks (Einführungsworte), 22. List Gespräch, Düsseldorf, 1988 Apr. 29 (Box 51)
    - 49. "Europa – Vision und Wirklichkeit" (Europe – vision and reality), speech, Rheinisch-Westfälisches Institute für Wirtschaftsforschung, Essen, 1988 May 18 (Box 51)
    - 50. "Eröffnung der Internationalen Verkehrsausstellung (IVA) '88" (Opening of the internationl transportation exhibition 1988), speech, Hamburg, 1988 May 31 (Box 51)
    - 51. "How Competitive Do You See American Companies, Including Your Own? Why Did You Invest in the U.S.?" speech, International Monetary Conference, Chicago, 1988 June 6. (Box 51)
    - 52. "Restructuring of the Steel Industry in Germany," speech, Unilever Manager's National Conference, Hoevelaken, Netherlands, 1988 June 13. (Box 51)
    - 53. "Strukturwandel am Beispiel Thyssen" (Structural change considering as example Thyssen), speech, Kongress Wissenschaft und Wirtschaft, "Erfahrungen in der Kooperation – Perspektiven für den Strukturwandel," Herne, 1988 July 5 (Box 51)
    - 54. "Integrity, Innovation, Involvement and Interdependence," speech, Automotive News World Congress, Detroit, 1988 July 17. (Box 51)
    - 55. "The External Implications of the Single European Market," paper, Royal Institute of International Affairs/Confederation of British Industry, London, 1988 Oct. 11. (Box 51)
    - 56. "Remarks on 1992 Policies with Special Emphasis on External Relations," speech, Merck European Advisory Council, Amsterdam, 1988 Oct. 13. (Box 51)
    - 57. "Perspectives nouvelles pour notre vieux continent" (New prospects for an old continent), speech, Cercle Franco-Allemand, Paris, 1988 Nov. 22. (Box 51)
    - 58. "Chancen und Gefahren des Industriestandortes Deutschland" (Opportunities and dangers of the German industrial base), speech, Augsburger Symposium, 1989 Mar. 1 (Box 51)
    - 59. "Europa 1992 – Chancen und Risiken" (Europe 1992 – opportunities and risks), speech, Niedersächsischer Wirtschaftsabend, Hanover, 1989 Apr. 6 (Box 51)
    - 60. "Die künftigen EG-Aussenbeziehungen zwischen Liberalität und Protektionismus" (The future European Community external relations between liberality and protectionism), speech, Expertengespräch der List Gesellschaft, Frankfurt, 1989 Apr. 14 (Box 51)
    - 61. "Perspektiven der Wirtschaftspolitik für Nordrhein-Westfalen" (Aspects of the economic policy for North Rhine-Westphalia), speech, Jahresversammlung Amerikanische Handelskammer, Düsseldorf, 1989 Apr. 28 (Box 51)
    - 62. "The United Kingdom and the Federal Republic of Germany on Course for 1992 – A German View," speech, Deutscher Industriekreis, London, 1989 May 18. (Box 51)
    - 63. "Der Einigungsprozess Europas – Erfahrungen und Perspektiven aus unternehmerischer Sicht" (The European unification process – experience and prospects from the entrepreneurial viewpoint), speech, Hanns-Martin-Schleyer-Stiftung, Innsbruck, 1989 May 19 (Box 51)
    - 64. "EG-Binnenmarkt – Vision und Wirklichkeit" (European Community single market – vision and reality), speech, Bundesverband Deutscher Stahlhandel, Neuss, 1989 Sep. 15 (Box 51)
    - 65. "The World of Materials – A European View," speech, American Society for Metals (ASM), Indianapolis, Indiana, 1989 Oct. 3. (Box 51)